this is software engineering radio the
podcast for professional developers on
the web at se - radio dotnet
HESA radio brings you relevant detailed
discussions about software engineering
topics at least once a month thanks to
our audience and the partners listed on
our website for supporting the podcast
[Music]
welcome listeners to new episode of
software engineering radio in this
episode we were once again going to talk
about something that relates to Scala we
had two episodes in Scala already an
introduction a long time ago and the
kind of update with Mizuno turski I
guess maybe five or six or seven
episodes ago this episode is going to be
in a very interesting Scala project a
middleware project called akka you
probably heard about it and on the other
end of the Skype connection is Yunus
Parral the chief developer I guess and
inventor of akka right yeah started off
a couple years ago is only me but now
last year or year and a half there's
been a team effort some some great
individuals right so I guess Victor
clanging I think it's one night I always
read about on Twitter yeah of the key
core developers amazing guy and they
have others great developers as well so
I'm just I'm just I'm just one in wine
that won't wanting to heard well you're
certainly the face that those people
associate with calm so do you want to
introduce yourself a little bit so
people know who we're talking to sure
my name is Eunice Lanier and I live in
Sweden
a small town calypso outside Stockholm I
have been involved with Scala for a five
number five years now I got it before
scholar at the store I started getting
to functional programming in general
when I started off using Erlang and then
the long story short I got I got really
excited about our long I try to get
people excited about it in clients and
colleagues and so on but it was really
hard for to to push through them because
it has a you just it makes the lease an
excellent language but it has its own
runtime it has its own library and so on
so so but I just basically felt it was
it was too many good things to just be
left to these are
or Erlang geeks and I wanted to to move
over or some of these concepts onto the
JVM so I started acha about about two
and a half years ago something like that
before that I worked at the JVM
clustering company called the terracotta
ah right and in the beginning in the
mean time between terracotta naka I was
running my own consultancy firm as well
and prior to terracotta that wish I
worked for about four four or five years
I worked for ba systems at the J rocket
team the JVM team they have team here in
Stockholm since we in Sweden so I mean
having been mainly involved in writing
middleware products and systems and and
and in also consulting in the area of
concurrency scalability right into the
server side and handle data of the stack
you can say yeah so when I looked at
Scala sorry when I looked at a car it's
clearly obvious that Erlang isn't an
inspiration right so do you want to give
us an overview of what archives and
maybe what the main influences flow from
Erlang are I mean we will talk about the
various modules and stuff later but just
to collect kind of ten thousand ten ten
thousand foot overview yeah sure it is
definitely influenced by but also by
some other some other languages and and
and Tim ten tools out there they say
I've tried I've tried to sort of put
together a bunch of a bunch of Tilson
and and ways of thinking that in
interest to regular Java developer might
sound a little bit alien but but that
solves the concurrency and the
scalability and the fault tolerant story
in a very neat way so from from airline
we adopted the the actor model of
concurrency but but the which is even an
even better model over did over
distributed computing we also adopted
the the Erlang style of
tolerance and reliable reliability and
also some sometimes known as a let it
crash embraced failure we can talk more
about that in detail yep
hey there so so we use we use actors for
that for the for that as well so we use
actors for both scaling up on multi-core
architectures meaning embrace and concur
concurrency and we also use actors for
scaling out from on multiple JVMs you
know I mean you can do that regardless
in the same restriction the same
runtimes you basically run writing you
write your code once and not thinking
about either of these if you work with
inside the sort of the actor model you
are versus or prepare your application
to scale either up or out and sometimes
both and and since you have this level
of indirection the runtime can actually
even take that decision for you it
should be scaled up around
so in some sense you're saying that
developers once have to learn something
that may feel a bit strange in the
beginning but then they're kind of
settled and can do everything they need
yeah more or less
I want to respond to that that actors
are sometimes in my email in many cases
an excellent tool for the job but there
are certain kind of problems that actors
can't solve at all where the actor model
sort of falls apart and that is that is
for example when you need when you need
consensus across many many concurrent
components or even distribute the
components extra service it implements
the contrary all that the implements
shared state no no sorry nothing or
tzedakah check pure message-passing yeah
and and the classic way you solve that
inner line in any and in other tools
that empower or frameworks that
implement that is by Charlaine air
everything down into database in in in
in Erlang yet amnesia database or or if
you're if you're in the Java space you
would probably put it in in Mar sequel
or or something and and only to in doing
that only when you need something like
consensus is extremely
expensive why should you pay for that
for the foot out for the the IO overhead
and and the disk I will both discs in
Network IO and stuff like that when you
only want agreement between two
components there are in process and and
living in two different threads and for
you know in or just just to solve that
problem in it in a more neat way in a
much much more performant way is
something will software transactional
memory that gives you a transactional
memory basically gives you what you have
in Oracle and we begin begin commit but
in memory
priced at it's extremely fast and that
solves a set of problems that you can
solve with actors and then on top of
that we have another couple did the
different abstractions over over
concurrency and over over distributed
computing that that solves yet another
set of problems out so our case more of
a toolkit isn't it doesn't sort of man
ISM dictates the the rule so you need to
do it like this and that and so on it's
more it more gives you a set of
orthogonal tools with that that we has
high cohesion that you can use nice
together and mix and match just is to
solve your your problem right so so
let's maybe look at these various tools
building blocks components modules right
yeah let's start with actors we did have
an episode on Erlang a long long time
ago or a long time ago so people might
have heard about actors and there are
obviously also other languages and
frameworks that allow actor based
programming models but I think it's
still useful to give a quick recap of
what actors are and then we can discuss
what they are how they are specifically
implemented in danaka sure the actors
are you can think about actors very much
as obvious as objects to the end they
encapsulate
state and behavior they are however more
encapsulated than well then then what
I'm sort of in standard classes in many
languages and instances in many other
languages in a way there are even more
they are more object oriented and then
then what anything you can find in Java
C C++ and so on
today they implement what is well share
nothing or cachoeira nothing's our
encapsulation of state that means that
the stake inside an actor cannot be
viewed by any other actor you can't be
at be accessed in any in any way so
there's there's no way another actor can
anyone can influence the the so this is
the state of another actor without sort
of sending in MMS isn't telling that
that actor updated state internally so
so it is it completely I mean the other
end of what we are used to in Java where
we have Oracle shares taking currency
where we were everything even though you
know you might encapsulate aerobics
nicely into classes and then use private
variables and stuff in the concurrency
environment you have it encapsulated
anything because threats they don't obey
these rules they run into a menu just
straight across your your classes and ER
and or your instances are we rather say
and not not sort of playing again with
any of the the encapsulation rules that
you know just says set up in your inner
inner inner type system and and and that
means that you need to do a lot of
plumbing in order to to to to introduce
serve safety and determinism into your
into your code by by added by out by
adding locks
however the and the actor model E is
certainly sort of raises the abstraction
level in a way that that it it it solves
that problem for you
actors are by themselves the nature of
actors are that they are thread-safe
and there's no way you can get
stale stale data race conditions the
soil and so on within within the actor
itself and and so all the plumbing is
sort of taken care of for you by the
FERC by the runtime and you as a
developer can instead focus on on
writing the business logic and and they
could they could the concurrency is
actually lifted from from from plumbing
to workflow so so with actors used you
think in workflow how messages flow in
the system right instead instead of how
you should protect yourself from others
in with by introducing blocks so I guess
that's that's maybe that the core thing
right so that actors only communicate by
a message passing that's the only way
they can talk to the outside or
specifically to other actors exactly
exactly so something so the way the way
that actors are different from objects
is also that each each actor has has a
mailbox that is sort of a message queue
and if I want to communicate with an
actor I need to send it a message and
that message will end up in his mailbox
and it does it doesn't mean that if I
send a message to tune actor that I will
sit and wait until that message has been
processed right but but if you're used
to to programming in with JMS or mq
series and so on the the mall is very
similar to that in that messages are
sent in an asynchronous fashion some
people call it programming without a
call stack so it doesn't the only thing
it does it it puts the message onto
there the receivers mailbox and it
returns right and it's up to the
scheduler to dispatch that message on to
that actor whenever it's is that actors
turn to get to get the meantime slice
all processing on an owner on a thread
and so from from an actor's implemented
or from the perspective of somebody who
writes an actor you basically put in a
repeat forever loop that looks into the
mailbox
and sees if there is something and maybe
blocks if there is nothing and then
unblocks if there was something again
the current oh yes but the important
thing did an important difference is
that actors never block right they only
conceptually photos are completely they
are term lazy they are reactive in a way
that an actor doesn't do anything unless
it's being told and and when an actor is
sort of blocking conceptually if she
blocking in quotes it is it is suspended
so it doesn't consume any resources yeah
well me what I meant by that it's not an
active while loop that really drives
around forever it if there is nothing in
the mailbox the threat that owns the
actor or the other way around is kind of
suspended and it's really can't if there
is another mail bomb a done the mailbox
messenger mailbox exactly like this what
this allows you to is to write systems
where you have where you have not only
thousands of actors as you can have with
threads but you can have tens of
thousands hundreds of thousands but
easily mid millions of actors because
actors are only constrained strained by
memory that's the only resource that you
thank you that they can sue well but but
you still have to have to have a kind of
threat pool that you allocate
dynamically to an actor and in some
sense this size of this threat pool may
be limits the number of concurrently
active actors right okay more cores give
you more performance because more actors
can actually run in parallel yeah very
important yeah so you said that there is
absolutely no way actors can communicate
with the outside world and they have no
shared stay with anybody except through
messages so that basically means that
those messages have to have value
semantics in the sense that the data
that's passed from one actor to another
one is kind of passed by value and not
by reference right it's very important
and inner line it is easier because
inner line each actor has its own heap
you can say that is that it's completely
isolated from from from from another
actors heap but akka is implemented in
scala that that runs on the JVM and they
we just have one single massive sherry
yep so so this actually puts a little
bit of a burden onto the developer that
the developer means to make sure that
all messages are immutable okay that's
exactly what what you said it I just
wanted to stress that that is the
limitation that we that is hard to to
avoid ooh living on the only JVM yeah so
but I mean if you have actually
distributed actors on different VMs or
different machines then you obviously
have copy or copy semantics of value
semantics you can't even avoid that but
if you are local then that is actually
kind of an overhead so it's there's some
kind of clever optimization that really
uses mmm
you know like pass by reference but it
kind of really ah I just got it because
it's immutable you you actually do pass
the reference but nobody can change ah
you mean we don't do anything the JVM
make sure that it optimizes that for us
right so just and in a way that is that
is one over one above one of the reasons
why why actors implementations in
general on the JVM if they are well
written can easily outperform actors on
on Erlang little bit but that is them
but I will probably get flame for saying
that this because as always I mean in
micro benchmarks you can't prove
anything you you want but that is an
advantage I would rather say that what
that we have right it's noise water
garden for a developer but on the other
hand you can get way better throughput
by avoiding a lot of copying so yeah so
so I learned that one difference between
Erlang and Scala actors or should say
akka actors because Scala has its own
actors as well is that there is actually
passed by reference and you use value
objects to make sure that you don't
actually kind of share mutable state are
there are other significant differences
between Erlang and Scala I should say
akka
and you have you haven't sure I'm in
there they are they are there syntactic
difference there right so of course and
and but I would say I would say I mean
there are a lot of people coming over
from our line to using our characters
and they they usually feel pretty much
at home because we have we have tried to
to maintain a lot of the same semantics
so there shouldn't be not very few
surprises coming from our alignment
error our line has used has been using
actors since early eighties ransom and
and and it is the DD factor or server
standard for how to implement actor
based concurrency you can say so if we
felt that we didn't want to submit take
your misstep just step away from that
more than necessary in there and there
are areas where we have perhaps taking a
different route but in most cases we
have not so DIF easy is it is in the
runtime rusty I mean how do JP n behaves
compared to the ER line yeah okay I mean
it's interesting to see because I always
thought that one of the reasons why
Erlang is as great and scalable and cool
as it is is because of its runtime I
always said kind of or like a small like
an application server or framework than
a programming language so yeah the road
me is amazing right I mean but but but
very much depending on your on your on
on your use case yeah I mean early is a
dynamically type language in ensure you
have you have high performance oil and
the hype optimizer they don't the other
hand my my my experience using both and
although I've lived most of my life on
the JVM is that min for for writing
really high high throughput low latency
applications and almost nothing beats
beats the JVM if you if you're if you're
using the JVM the right way and not not
not complicating things it's so
extremely good at optimizing things so
I wouldn't want to use anything else
okay so there are I mean I said that a
couple of times unfortunately so there
are also actors directly in Scala
they're actually a part of the Scala
runtime or standard library why not use
those how are your actors different than
those in Scala standard Scala yeah
the first iteration ibaka was when I was
using Scala library actors so to speak
but I moved away from them in stand and
Andrea and swapped them for my own after
having some some some problems with them
we have first we have performance and
throughput issues and then we also have
some memory leaks and so on and and so
that was sort of forced into creating my
own actor so also I wanted to have a
more but much more some open the
implementation in terms of how you can
configure it class we we have tried to
make it almost every little knob open so
you can tweak in tune and and we have
different schedulers that you can swap
pick and you and they can make a huge
difference in in different kind of use
cases and and yeah so we were I think we
with whips are taking the disk all
actors and and and and push the limits
even even even further and and now we're
actually we're working on on replacing
the Scala library I contacted without
actors and but not leaving over the
South Africa developers out in the cold
because we got we going to re-implement
some of the features that the skull
actors have that akka doesn't so we sort
of try to make the best of both worlds
Oh coming in Scala 210 probably anybody
years okay or nine months or so so one
thing I never really understood is the
following so there are kind of two in
concurrent programming there are maybe
three kind of hives or hot topics one is
actors the other one is STM's we'll talk
about that in a minute and the third one
is functional program
I understand why functional programming
is useful you know you don't have any
side effects blah blah blah value
semantics blah blah blah all great how
to functions and actors fit together or
don't they fit together and it's kind of
an accident that Scala as a functional
or object-oriented functional language
has actors so is there any benefit of
having functional abstractions with
actors together it is it is it is a the
short answer is that there's not much in
common right but but but the long a
little bit longer answer is that I 10 I
normally use them both together because
I I use actress a little bit more
coarse-grained to implement more
components and services and inside the
actors I use functional programming so I
understand for example that the way the
the Akaka actors are written kind of if
you will a kind of internal skylight
ezel uses functional things and you know
closures and stuff I think but what you
just said is basically if you use
functional programming within actors
then these this functional program or
these functional programs are not
concurrent anymore because your unit of
concurrency is the actor so use
functional programming just because it's
more concise and nicer and high order
functions parallel but not for any
concurrency reason yeah yeah ok the main
we we do have something agents that that
that takes the functional angle the
formal perspective on actors you can say
and I'm just going to explain them in a
second I first I just want to explain
the reasoning why we wanted to add them
and that is that an actress are are a
little bit hard to compose because they
they are they are objects right there
and then and they and they are they are
all Victorian orient
and the normal way you you you you you
do like abstractions and really use you
know oh is through classic inheritance
and that is normally the way you you
compose and you extend and reuse actors
however in the function of the world you
don't want that you don't you want
function composition right yep and
that's why we added eight yet it's
Agence is something that we haven't
invented ourselves is something that
comes from from the language closure
right and it's it's a very neat way of
using the actor style but from a
functional perspective and what ages
does you you know we talked about actors
being having encapsulating state and
behavior and you're sending immutable
messages to an actor so basically you're
sending stupid state two men a
synchronously to the behavior because
they behavior is you see inside inside
the act like components the if a
procedural interface in some sense okay
it's asynchronous but the behavior is
all in the components aka actors and
then you send around pure data exactly
exactly like back and they they invert
that they ages is an agent is basically
a memory slot that you can put something
in a bucket you can put a map in there
or a vector or or just an integer or
something and an agent allows you to
send asynchronous instead of sending a
stupid data holder or an immutable
messages you can send a function to the
agent asynchronously and have that being
applied in an atomic fashion to that
bucket but that works only in process
right for me this works only in process
RS is also possible to do remote we
artists actors currently are only in
process but nothing but it would prevent
us from doing them them remote because
they are really written using actors and
we have remote actors so so so this not
be something that people have asked for
so much
but nothing would prevent that but but
the whole idea is that instead of
sending behavior instead of setting
state to the behavior sending behavior
to the state and then and now since you
are sending a function you can compose
that function in any way you want before
you send it that means he uses a
differently even with different
implementations depending on context
from where it's being used and how it's
being used and so this is the way you
can approach sort of the the a station
canners act or message passing style
model to a functional lens okay am i
kind of wrong or that's already kind of
lead into the STM story because I think
the way software transactional memory is
implemented in closure is at least one
of the mechanisms also these agents that
you have something where the access to
shared state is kind of controlled and
guarded and what you do is you send
functions and they are kind of
coordinated through a kind of mailbox
right yeah so it leads into and another
you can say because what these eight is
are they are transaction aware you know
in arc and they're also in closure right
so so what they are is that what they do
is if they are being applied if the
function is being applied to an agent
then it will look out in the content
agency is there a transaction running if
there is transaction running then it
will join that transaction and what this
means is that the function will not be
applied to the agent unless the
transaction commits so you could hold
off until until there is a successful
commit of the transaction and then it
will flush flush this buffer of all
functions and and that means that you
can compose them so you can have many
agents during the same transaction and
you know that either all are applied
successfully or none are and also
it's agents are similar to how STM is
used in ACTA because STM is Enoch a is
used using worse will banished
references and those also happen to be
memories law right but the difference
between these matters references and
agents that are used in a transactional
fashion is that is that agents are
asynchronous why why the manage
references or not okay I see so I mean
we don't want to do audio programming
here by having you read source code but
can you give us a little bit of a flavor
how how the API for actors and for this
agent stuff kind of looks and tactically
I mean just a little bit of an idea sure
starting with starting with with actors
we if we're looking at first I want to
say the skull has a job I in a scarlet
no I guys in Scala and Java API okay so
you you can use you can use though
everything we said this DM agents and
actors from Java as well just requires
ten times the amount of code I guess you
know sometimes we try to make it but if
we want to talk about the scholarly API
now that since we're coming from a
scholar angle already is that yeah if
you want people need them at an actor we
have something called we have a trait
call actor and a trait is just it like
it makes in it's an implementation well
in with like an interface with an
implementation so you can make study
into any kind of class but basically you
say whatever
fooey extends actor and then you need to
implement one thing and that is the
receiver method and the receive method
implements the message handler for that
actor and and in scala we you using
Patran match to match on the message
that comes in so basically a case case
message one case message to case message
three and when it does matching on on
which message arrived in the mailbox ins
being dispatched
now
and then it runs the handler for that
message that's basically how it's how
both what it looks like and in all all
code all state that you have now inside
the actress members member variables or
completely thread-safe who you'll need
to have this volatile or atomic
references and stuff like that an agent
however is less code because it's just a
memory slot so they'll if you if you
want to write an alien you you only say
agent and then parenthesis and then
whatever value you want to you want to
put in there can be you can put in the
map or a completely in a something else
you can even say you don't want a value
you just want to type you can then say
agent square brackets in true some and
and then you have a message methods will
send that you can send a function okay
to that a so that's basically with
Luke's the SDM it's very similar then
you then then you just say ref or EF and
parenthesis and then you wrap the value
and then then that values then managed
by by the SDM and and fully
transactional yeah we also have
transactional data structures that
doesn't that this sort of gives you a
rest a nurse call a map interface but
it's transactional under the hood so
then it removes to almost all bit walls
for visible traces of the plumbing
serves me so when I came over came
across a transactional memory first time
I don't know when that was I can have
always saw this keyword atomic and then
between the braces you would do stuff
and closure as well as akka use a more
explicit way of doing things by
explicitly putting those memory contents
that should be transaction alized into
these references and then you have to
explicitly interact with the reference
instead of with the data that remember
is holds is that just syntactic sugar or
is there something is there a difference
that I don't that I don't seem to
understand you're talking about why why
we are both retaking enclosure and
is having a very explicit yep way of
using transact esteem so it's a reason
not all of the memories transactional
right only the things in the trend in
the in the so it's okay yeah you
explained exactly and and the reason is
basically because I I've been I've
historically been a bit skeptic with SDM
the the earliest games they were they
used a lot of magic bar code rewriting
basically in allowing the user to to to
mess around with it with it's in his
state in any kind of weird ways and then
the then the SDM would just come in and
bless the whole thing and it will just
work correctly and I'm I'm I don't I'm a
non-believer in that we'll see okay III
think that it's being explicit if it's
not too much verbosity in the code is a
good thing because you know when you
serve both pay the price all of the
performance it but also you know you
know explicitly when when things went
sort of the SDM is affecting your code
and you can you can be very very very
fine-grain in which state needs to be
transactional in which state should not
even be in transaction and then I sort
of like being explicit the actor model
is a very explicit way of of concurrency
and and be been not not trying to like
lie or Horrors or sort of pretend that
we have shared memory and the way we
don't have it and the estimates are even
I'm an extension of that I want to have
it explicit and I think this is a
general tendency right I mean when you
look back at the beginnings of Oh Oh
everything was an object and everything
was try to make it or everything try to
make it look like local object-oriented
communication also even if the object
were remote like in COBOL Java RMI and
then you had these orthogonal
persistence thingies right where you
would automatically persist objects and
so on and so on but of course the
non-functional properties of remote or
persistent data are completely different
and now I think there is a tendency to
make these things explicit not try to
hide it you can see that in ZOA or rest
and as you just say also in your
kind of STM implementation I guess
that's maybe a general tendency right
yeah I think I think and I think it's a
healthy tendency you know some things
should not be be hidden I think unis I
mean concurrency is one thing that is
easier to hide but but the network is
almost impossible to hide I mean if you
want to if you want to hide the network
you will always lie regardless I mean
sometimes you lie better and sometimes
were Christmas but it will always be a
lie like if it's a very very leaky
abstraction that leaks way too much in
most implementations I've seen that
tries to hide this but it was actors are
remote able in Akaka right and their
syntax doesn't change so in that sense
that's transparent yeah and that is well
that was one of the key things that we
wanted to achieve that then you write
directors as these living things like
these these active components and and it
shouldn't matter if they should be
should be be used in in a single
threaded environment in a multi-threaded
environment or in a multi JVM
environment and and what we do instead
of trying to raise a fraction so much
should we high that everything is is
local we actually do the the universe we
say that everything is as it is
distributed yep so so so we use
message-passing even though it's in
process we just use mute obvious use
message passing and that allows us to
just like stretch it out onto multiple
JVM or even even data centers without
sort of lying or that is shared memory
so so actors really implement completely
location transparent distributed
computing what you do is that you get
when you create an actor you don't get
an instance or reference to that actor
directly but instead you get a reference
to to that actor indirectly you get a
pointer inner line you have something
called pit the process item in akka is
called actor ref and it's the same idea
so this pit or this actor F in ARCA can
be
used in processed and to talk to local
actor we could also use improv mean on
one machine to talk to a remote actor
and the client doesn't need to know
he sends messages and and are these then
kind of proxies with a strongly typed
interface that only allows the messages
that you kind of handle or our actor
interfaces generic in that sense that
they accept any message and then they're
kind of this college if you don't know
how to handle them
yeah that's a very good person that
leads us into in in chacas two different
types of actors okay we have the
classics or style of actor is that is is
dynamically typed you can say even
though Scala is a statically typed
language the way we implement actors in
the classic sense is babies making them
dynamically typed well that means is
that you can send any kind of message to
an actor and it does dispatching on what
kind of type it is basically but usually
is using work you see it uses call up
after matching to be more intelligent
than just yeah
and that means that you can send
messages to an actor that an actor
cannot respond to and but but there so
that is something that you need to deal
with but on the other hand what you can
do and what we do allow in our in in
ARCA is to swap the actor implementation
so so there so there might be different
source stages in an actor's life cycle
you can see an actor as the state
machine and and I mean in a specific
when you start up an actor it might be
able to respond to two to one or two or
three types of messages but then it can
internally swap this implementation to
be able to receive another kind of type
of messages so it can change the the its
API basically and then messengers each
can they can respond to dynamically of
course it doesn't change the API right
it's not visible to the outside what the
inside can handle now so that I mean
that that I guess that's that that's the
thing right felt found very powerful in
early in early early I'm being attacked
we typed language that's not right there
yeah
but we were able to encode that in in
Scala in a way that feels very natural
so you can in if you if from from within
an actor you just say become and then
you pass in then the new implementation
so then you can sort of say I want to
become something else but you can also
send send an actor implementation from
the outside using CID by sending
hot-swap message that is less useful I
would say it's a little bit more
dangerous but they can be useful
sometimes but but I tend to use it's
become they actually can redefine itself
very often actually but that is
basically did the bridge pattern right
you have different different
implementations for the same thing yeah
yeah you also have Hydra
you also have typed actors right that
today have a strongly typed API then yes
it does and and that can be very useful
some some some some times basically what
what we're doing then is it'll allow you
to encode accuracy by using an interface
with the responder methods interface in
Java or trait in Scala and then a
regular pulled your regular standard
Java Scala object as the implementation
and then we rewrite these are the
internals of them all that support if
you would just create it using new and
then whatever class it is then it will
become a regular that's under object but
we but if you instead created through a
factor that we have then then what what
what we are returning is through
something very similar to the active
object pattern that each method each
time you sort of invoke a method on that
interface that method is turned or that
method invocation is turning into the
message we wrap the all them in the
arguments to the method into a message
and put that asynchronously
on a queue to be processed by the
internal pojo so but when it reaches to
stop the pojo it's again kind of turned
into a method call on the POJO yeah okay
so
basically an indirection a queue in
between the actual kind of interface and
implementation yes yes okay and we
rewrite void methods into fire forget
and we rewrite something the methods
that return something we rewrite to two
methods to to message send that returns
something call the future okay cool so
you can sort of use any kind of method
dispatch both so far forget and and also
request reply what do you do with
exceptions we exceptions we make sure
that we transfer them from the from the
act from big actor from the receivers
thread into the callers thread and turn
through so that's expected that are
thrown on the proxy yeah it
synchronously no can't be no they know
whenever they they happen on in in the
in this or receivers thread we using the
standard and miss or message passing so
we send it we saw we we pass a reply
method back into into the callers thread
and there we threw our extra okay so how
about but forget this how does this work
with the futures because I mean futures
are an object you get and then us the
client you kind of ask the future for
the actual value whenever you feel ready
and you maybe the value is there maybe
it's not there
so it's kind of a pole mode but then if
if you use kind of how do you through
when and how do you throw the exception
I mean the client might be off doing
completely different things we have
three different ways of doing it if your
only returns for example a string if you
have a something that passes hit a a
method it takes the string a rich it
returns a string we do not expose the
future to the to the end user but we
inside the implementation we we get the
future and then we do an await without
returning the value unlit until we get
either the timeout
we get an exception or we get the return
value so from the clients perspective
it's like a blocking call yeah exactly
hmm then I understand where the
exception is thrown right that makes
sense yeah but we also allow you to to
actually in there in the interface
create a method that returns an ARCA
future and in that sense you are in
control
that method will be returned immediately
and you can can can can dig into desire
to do the blocking await or you can
register and from a non complete
callback to let them know or you can
check you did it complete with an
exception did it complete with a value
okay so but if you do a proxy with a
blocking call on the client side then
the whole benefit of the actor model and
the asynchrony only shows up on the
server which becomes more scalable the
client kind of will will have only a
limited number of kind of threats and if
they're all blocked then the client is
out of lock lock yeah yeah yeah we do we
do have the same request reply kind of
style of development for this well this
on target for these dynamically typed
actors as well yeah that allows you to
to to send a message and then just say
reply and it will reply with the future
but we we are trying to tell people to
avoid the using blocking in future calls
as much as possible we have shown in
benchmark that it can they can in limit
your your throughput by two to one third
of your of what you could get if you you
seeing unblocking calls yeah because you
are using some kind of synchronized
blocking thingy again which is the yeah
you're sitting on the thread yeah and
then you could consume the resources and
if you do that for like a thousand
simultaneous calls we can really can run
it we can run all the threads right what
we have added now in akka Wanda Wanda
this came out a couple of weeks ago is
is a completely non blocking API to
futures use it allows you to to get to
get a number of futures and work
composing their meatman without blocking
and then then so you can actually do
operations and calculations based on on
not yet completed values and and you can
choose to block on the on the on the
final computation and didn't delay it as
long as possible and it also he we even
added something called a on complete
callback so that allows you to to
register function to being told when the
value arrives and if you used that there
there is no blocking at all right so but
that requires some Scala metric right
you can't do that easily in job I at
least not with an acceptable syntax now
you need to have this ugly interface
sort of style of functions right see new
new new function and then and then
implement the run methods gonna ask you
why you selected Scala I mean is it just
because it was the language of the day
where we were just interested or does
Scala have any specific properties that
makes a car well I mean of course you
can implement everything with ugly
syntax like in Java but but how
important is Scala for making work what
a car does yeah I think what it mainly
enabled me was is to deliver the ARCA
platform at runtime so much so much so
much so much faster I think it is using
many mutability at the core using all
the excellent data structures inside
Scala and and so one has Manavi writing
similar systems myself I mean for being
part of the Terra Cotta riding a
scalable middleware and be a with logic
and stuff and and and III feel that I'm
I'm much more confident in the code
there I write in Scala it's it's less
bugs it's less code to both write and to
maintain and to understand this list it
lifts the abstraction level so it's more
reason about actually the actual
implementation value rather than a lot
of plumbing I think
and and and it also fits fits very nice
with with scholar the horrible approach
of immutability and an embracing
concurrency and I also think that that I
could have of course I mean India time
written the same thing with the same
performance in in Java but the amazing
thing is that Scala can actually gives
you the same performances and they're
actually almost in tentacle barcode as
you get with Java and and there are and
there aren't really any languages out
there that like on the rest of the JVM
that can give you that most of the
languages are dynamically typed and they
are out of the question so Scala can't
really take I mean they can't really at
least for what I'm writing I may have
they're made you know where web web
applications and then writing stuff that
it aren't perform is critical but I
could never I could never use it to
write middleware but I can use scholar
to write middleware in the same ticket
we can't really take javis place there
and I think that's that's pretty amazing
hmm so let's talk a bit about fault
tolerance you already mentioned that you
use erlangs let it crash style which
basically means that one actor monitors
another one and if the other one dies
because it crashes then this you know
it's kind of a new one is started it's a
kind of correct summary yeah yeah yeah
so some very well why why we use it yeah
basically because I mean that allows
that in short allows us to you to write
system that can heal themselves they you
can you can declare to the configure the
way the system should respond to failure
instead of instant in standard classic
Java style error handling you you
literally first you have you have what
you're so critical state the the real
really core business state you usually
have littered throughout the whole
application secondly you normally
program extremely defensively by using
the try catch is everywhere you're
paranoid trying to prevent their error
from a front from happening but if you
if you if you if you write systems like
this
I mean high-performance and especially
distributed computing you know that
failure is the minute right there's
nothing that you can't you cannot
prevent it will happen regardless if you
want or not and instead of trying to
code it defensively it this way of the
writing fault or encode embraces failure
and sees it as in natural state only
about Application Lifecycle is it is as
natural to crash as it is to boot boot
up and to start into dispatch this
message successfully and this gives you
a way of thinking about the problem
basically that that first it gives you a
granularity of programming the failure
management yeah that that syrup can can
help you to to to to have the system
repair itself it's kind of like a global
exception handler right if something
goes wrong restarted please yeah I mean
it doesn't breastfeed it feet or
problems but but but I've used it in a
whole wide range of different problems
or clients and and and and with a lot of
success and and and basically I mean the
whole idea is that you use a reset your
your your components into stable state
and and can continue right and and and
the way you normally organize your
programs like this is to write them like
like an onion so you you have your inner
most critical state insight in the inner
lucky in the inner most they see inside
the on it and then you had will have
layers of defense you can stage you have
third we are first line of defense and
second line of defense the third line of
defense and and requests coming in from
a user usually hist your your your
outermost line of defense and and then
it usually takes a lot from this for the
arrow to propagate all the way
into the inner most critical and
precious core of your of your system the
way is the way I normally write my
applications that if I'm holding on to
some critical state that is important to
me
and I'm supposed to do something then I
never do it myself
I always create an actor and delegate to
him to do that for me if he dies that's
fine because I'm still okay and so by
having this level of indirection I can
knock and I can protect myself you know
in in a very nice way and this and this
whole thing becomes completely
declarative so you declaratively define
the rules for how this should set up and
the system take care of it by itself but
I guess setting up those rules then and
the relationships between the actors and
who checks who and who restarts who that
is can be non-trivial right I mean
getting something wrong there that means
everything is screwed how do you test
this how to get confident in that yeah
that is something that we're working
hard on in the ARCA team right now to
create good tools for testing I think
the problem is wider and then than just
testing that the components for failure
is it is that also that that you
normally tend to run all of these
components in different threads yeah and
it becomes a problem of testing things
concurrently very very easily we try to
help with that by profit for example
providing a dispatcher that basically
forces you to dispatch everything in one
single thread so you get you get
sequential serialized stew so
communication and that makes it much
easier to to to to to test and and we we
also have other tools in in the ARCA
test kit module that that allows you to
to choose or test this this concurrent
world in a more in the more is the
deterministic fashion okay basically but
it is a challenge definitely but I think
I think it's it's no less
Challenge than testing amendment in Java
style of applications with with with
with with try CAPTCHAs sure everywhere
yeah I think it sir lifts the the
problem a little bit to another level
not simplifying it but just approach it
differently the good thing is I guess
you have a clearly defined set of let's
say boundaries or interfaces which are
the actors and therefore putting in some
kind of tracing functionality that gives
you a time diagram or you know some some
some some print out or whatever that
shows the timing of the different
interactions is is easier to do than
kind of if you did that on on any level
within the implementation code when
we're talking about this is that if you
want if you want to write a concurrent
application in Java you normally use for
example the executor service and a
thread pool and you dispatch Horrible's
to do to do jobs yep if these die even
though you have a try cache or whatever
yeah and try to repair it if the thread
blows up the only thing you will see is
a stack trace all the way up to your
service normally because exceptions do
not jump between threads right no way
and very can be notified that that my my
buddy thread he died here yeah but using
this sort of linking and supervision
that is also called allows you to to
monitor other concurrent components and
get notifications across threads which
is a very non-trivial problem in writing
concurrent code and and I just I did
person I just love that I mean it's it's
early it's a lot of problems goes to go
through to fix that problem if you write
standard Java multi-threaded application
so I guess we kind of covered the core
of our call right the most important
things we covered I would think yeah
thanks so I think the essence that is
the three that this three sort of
cornerstones are a concurrence of
scalability and fault-tolerance
so I think I think that should that
should be the essence a lot yeah
and then we had a whole bunch of other
modules for interacting with it with the
rest of the world you can say like for
other services and other modules members
though I think you should give us a
brief overview at least of this stuff I
mean for example I wonder what the
spring integration is all about and a
qmp euro is GI rest I mean just give us
a little bit of an overview so we know
how to connect it to our existing world
yeah sure
this is said we have a spring module and
for that we are worried we're
integrating the ACA's typed actors into
the spring scene sokka's type two actors
are essentially spring beans they have
an imitation with an interface it's very
it's very natural we have a spring sort
of DSL you can say a custom namespace in
the application context or XML that
allows you to wire wrap event supervisor
hierarchies and creating remote to type
doctrine so old within spring so to
speak and it used to say you can use the
standard spring dependence injection to
inject stuff into your actors and stuff
like that so that's pretty neat we have
similar for the for for a Google juice
as well if you're introducing Google use
they're also using the typed actors
between sliding to the juice were nicely
yeah and we also have you also mention
briefly AMQP e we have a name QP module
and that's our abstract scene QP as
actors in a way so what is to be sure
people know what is what is m QP and
it's s for advanced Message Queuing
protocol is it is a standard that some
eventually investment banks led by JP
Morgan created because they felt they
were in the hands of of the big the big
messes q deliver remember Brooke Burke
same cue serious and and Tim and they
didn't want to pay any license fees any
longer so they want they created their
own specification that that's a
specification that's have taken off and
it was initially a brilliant
specification in little like the latest
through rim revisions have really have
received a lot of a lot of criticism
because it's been complicated but I
still think it's a pretty slick slick
specifications this intro or played
together with the Java was it called
Java message queue to have our messaging
interface am i right yeah I'm not really
familiar with exactly how most JMS
brokers now you or your story me
implementing on QP in AMQP protocol can
I meant JMS you mention me I was so you
would use JMS as the underlying
communication transport technology that
transport messages between actors no I
think yeah I think the other way around
actually because if it's a QP is that it
is a network Stanner is binary protocol
and say it is a protocol on the on than
on the network layer okay and and you've
probably used you could use some in the
JMS api but communication is all in but
if we forget jammers for a second just
talking to em QP means that your actors
are still the same but you plug them in
so they receive messages through AMQP
right okay the protocol for
communication is now ntp instead of r
cos a standard tcp based protocol okay
so get it yeah OC is there a story yeah
we have we had we had an attempt to make
everything in our cows GI enabled all
the modules but we it was true there
were too much pain in that so we had to
revert that but but but but currently
the the they are the octa-core
the akka actor dot jar in which you have
all the active person and and and that
stuff is those giant able now so if you
only use that then it's been it's an
issue can use those GI but
from that on I having to like to let my
users down my Kobalt solve that problem
at some point yeah yeah okay another
module that I wanted to to make sure we
cover is these the acha acha camera
modules what's kind of in the modern for
apache camel what is kept before the for
the department for me what is camel
camel is a framework to implement
enterprise integration patterns Wow it
is a ways it is basically dsl
domain-specific language for about for
wiring endpoints together cause you
might have stuff flowing in from JMS you
wanna you want to pipe them through
through using sort of some sort of
routing and perhaps replicating
something to AMQP when it's trouble said
time something down in just my sequel
database at the same time as you want to
shovel it into some other thing for
auditing and and it can basically
connect all these endpoints together in
in in in intelligent fashion and have
been having and have some plumbing done
in between and i can abstract that so
you basically if you look at it from
from the code perspective the only thing
you do is that you take a regular actor
is a with consumer and then it defined
once one single field with it with the
string defining the protocol so if so if
it should be temple if you define it
does HTTP for example so if you say
create a consumer and say HTTP and then
you start that actor that means that if
you use for example comes in and
browsers to specific to that date to be
URL and pull something it will end up as
a message inside my actor and i can act
upon that and then i can just say reply
to pull something back to the word to do
them too
and the nice thing is that if i want to
change the endpoint i only need to
change one thing a lot of code where
something from HTTP colon slash slash to
two for some JMS yeah then then it
becomes an action that receives JMS
message it consumes JMS message message
message into j + QP protocol it
Susy and QP messages and you have the
same thing for producer so so so
everything is actors it looked exactly
like actors you send and receive
messages but they end up and and and
flow through these all end end points
and it's a very sleek way of having
outgoing interact with with outside
world cool
there also a rest story I guess
everything today has to have some rest
sorry yeah akka has has an HTTP module
that has an implementation though there
was the initial call missed I don't know
if we want to rename it that gives you a
synchronous you know what miss means in
German right yeah you know you know that
I mean I was also told by some by some
Finnish developers that are currently
means something not that good in Finnish
but it's hard to find name yeah I think
you know you know language is right yeah
so this is this mist layer gives you a
synchronous HTTP and it uses first used
Jetta continuations but now using the
thermo three of else back to to to to be
able to resume and suspense it's been
really an HTTP connection or and and in
an actress way so so but basically you
get you get messages with a put get post
to all this stuff sent to your mess tube
to your actors in a slick way it's a
very he's a very low-level API but there
are other guys that have been built
pretty interesting stuff on top of it
for example one one frame ik will spray
that that were there was built mr.
Sinatra Ruby soon artists style DSL on
top of this akka mist low-level layer
but is it called spray it's called spray
yeah like SP or a why that's funny yeah
hairspray it's funny we just talked at a
conference about creating another DSL
for
graphical tears else called spray I
guess yeah I guess so
okay so yeah some other modules as well
one worth mentioning is FSM model for
finish state machines actors are often
or state machine yeah that's why I can
be looking into that
right okay so let's kind of wrap up by
kind of zooming out again and talking
about how and where ik has used so how
does it scale and how do you know yeah
that's a very good question we have we
have of course not testing it up to then
after the number of knows that we will
like to because it's a cost issue but
but so the biggest the biggest
installation that client and some tested
it in this is 274 course mm-hmm
yes that was a pretty big installation
and then and they were very pleased with
that and it passed with flying colors of
solace I can't mention the source for
that baby's word it's a pretty pretty
big installation and so so so it it
seems to do its job well and sometimes
to my surprise surprise it seems to work
yes as intended not always of course but
then we then we need to go in to fix
things but which is been around long
enough now and it means be used in
production for in some cases for North
two to two years so we've been so we've
been we mister reaping the benefits of
its being of it being in a public open
source products for so long I mean
people have come to confront contributed
ideas patches bug reports and and and so
on for long and due to that I think it's
in is it's in very good shape so other
any sizable uses from you know known
companies that use the stuff so as a way
of kind of dropping names yeah
some there's no need to think through so
this is always the problem but some of
them are or it's companies like like
like sweet sweet elevation are using it
cscc netherlands it's a prison very
large installation using it what else
and and they use it mostly as a back-end
for web applications is that fair to say
or or enterprise applications it's
actually being used in quite important
quite two different areas I would to say
it's always I wish I could I could just
name name name all the companies we're
working together with and with what they
using for it for but I can't but but but
in short I just want to say that that
most most user is actually out of the
finance industry so it's it's it's not
e-commerce it's it's it's like it's
beast is it use of trading applications
very very a lot of a lot of transactions
per section high through the low latency
it's also been used in betting gaming
it's a very simple you use cases you now
have you have a few huge number of
transactions per second flying in and
then MMO games as well as a standard
standard I will say but a more more more
classic like betting can see casino
style and also like sports betting style
style of companies it's all it's all
it's also used in in in in in simulation
and for for for likes or massive data
set crunching they have in in in doing
simulation and technologies and and also
some ecommerce of course like my but
it's it's not the biggest sort of
segment I would I would say okay but we
have we have a lot of social media and
then I remember that Twitter uses Scala
so do they use
as well and then I'm not I don't think
they are using are actually still the
day they they be writing a whole bunch
of homegrown solutions but there they
are they are very heavily dependent on
Scala they are on the same thing with
Foursquare and some of these other plan
he decides Bank simple by the way you're
using are kamesh Ronald a hawk upcoming
is there a story between a kind lift I
know that people are using them together
specific like integration story no no we
we have we don't need to great with any
with any web frameworks directly more
than others have written written
adapters so there's there is but there's
been some work done but lift and also
with play there is a scholar
listen akka play module for example and
and also those integrates with many of
the scholars and the miners all scholar
web frameworks between which we talk to
at least so far traveler stay away from
locking into specific word frame okay we
just tried to be easy to use with Annika
in the web framework okay so we were
planning to record this episode last
week but I didn't have time and
originally we were planning to do it two
weeks ago and you didn't have time
because as I noticed afterwards
something big was happening it's called
typesafe do you want to talk a bit about
it yeah sure I'm really excited about
time see it's been it's basically in my
company scalable solutions that initial
scale was a consultancy company under
which I developed doc and then later
became the product company around around
akka with Victor and with declaring and
some other guys we were fired and joined
forces together with marketing order his
company called Scala solutions than to
build a a stack on scar l'm a Scala's
the foundation and then a full a
full-blown stack with with middleware
and and tools and also integration with
various web frameworks and so on so we
we join forces we have launched
the company back in January but they
would lunch get about two weeks ago
together with this offering that the
typesafe stack that we have super
subscription support for and and and so
on is it's all it's all still open
source we're planning on having a
product some products sweet commercial
product later on but so far everything
is just it's just so open source this is
a highly tested package Scala akka and
also later SPT a simple build tool and
and some tool in the IDE to linger you
seem to have hired quite a number of
people from the Scala world I hear that
heiko is also going to be part of that
thing group yeah hyper starts June 1st
right that should be tomorrow
yeah I'm really yeah I'm very excited
about that we had some some great
developers from the akka team and from
the Scala solution the from all from
Marcus team but apart from that we also
been able to hire some great minds for
example the multiverse STM during the
dacha akalitis on the multiverse SDM
peter bands here he's part of typesafe
now we we hired mark hara who is the the
guy behind SPT the simple build a little
and in paul phillips is one of the
co-founders he's like the number the
second guy in the Scala compiler after
mark and yes there's a lot of great
minds here you've also hired people from
the sky like hips IDE so we can hope yes
we're working very hard on that in the
company now yeah yeah to to to try to
make it in not only usable but but bring
it up to eventually to the level of Java
that is the new idea that'll be the time
when I switch yeah you know I mean if
you have a strongly typed language with
all the potential for this great ide
supporting then you don't have a good
IDE it's kind of it kind of spoils that
you know I'm still hacking in a text
and I'm so used to that I've been living
in the in emacs in and then a text
maintenance on for so many years now so
I don't even think about it but I know
it's it is it is one of our big
challenges right and but I think we are
about to solve it that the latest
Eclipse plug-in Eclipse plug-in is very
very good and now we have a dedicated
team only making it better every every
release so in six months I think it will
be very very good cool so is there
something we forgot to talk about
anything else you want to say before we
shut this down exciting times for a
scholar and I really encourage people to
to try it out and and and and eventually
if they think might have problem have
scalability problems I think they should
look into a there's also a whole bunch
of other nice frameworks into those out
there the in the in the scala community
it's a fantastic community with the loss
of great developers and producing a lot
of great stuff so it's definitely worth
checking out
yeah if I bomb and you should you can
use still use a super nice Java API so
and I shouldn't prevent you from right
now Scala I think is closest to becoming
the next big language I think after Java
I'm not sure there will be a language
that will have the same like you know
general adoption as Java has her head
hat but Scala is clearly on track I
think so that's very exciting as you say
yeah another the next big language and
be all the people talking I think we
have it's so easy to create languages
now right it's in the barrier where the
since WebM is so low now so so so so and
people have gotten used to use many
different languages right as people are
not that afraid jumping between so I
think I mean we're stepping into the
polyglot world more and more it's
finally just to to to kind of his final
comment it's funny how although we get
more and more languages many of them
have
well have the the core have to set
dissimilar have similar features right
it's basically functional
object-oriented a bunch of meta
programming and then depending on
whether your dynamic or static you have
two different options kind of plan but
but there's a lot of common stuff
between all these languages yeah I mean
it is converging and a lot of the ideas
are almost all ideas are old forty years
old
yeah twenty years old so so mistress
aren't you I mean we're almost made full
a full full serve right now just what
comes out this time is better than that
it was 40 years ago
absolutely okay then thank you very much
for for being on the show I enjoyed it
very much I really like these language
middleware framework discussions and I
hope you liked it as well
yeah to be part of it thanks a lot for
letting me be on the show absolutely
you'll you'll be able to read what the
listeners think I think they'll like it
thank you thank you bye
thanks for listening to software
engineering radio as a radio is an
educational program brought to you by
hillside Europe if you want more
information about the podcast and the
other episodes visit our website at se -
radio dotnet if you want to support us
you can donate to the SA radio team via
the website or you can advertise for SA
radio for example by clicking on the
Digg reddit delicious and Slashdot
buttons or by talking about us on
Twitter and Facebook you can also
support us by joining team and
shouldering some of the work to contact
the team please send email to team at se
- radio net or if your feedback is
specific to an episode please use the
comments facility on the website so
other people can react to your comments
this episode of SU radio as well as all
other episodes are licensed under a
creative commons 2.5 license please see
the website for details
[Music]